[{"question":"A deltoid ridge occurs in:","a":"Radius","b":"Ulna","c":"Femur","d":"Humerus","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Multi-unit smooth muscles are found in the  wall of: ","a":"Large blood vessels","b":"Intestine","c":"Stomach","d":"Urinary bladder","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Phalangeal formula of hand of man is:","a":"1,2,2,2,2","b":"2, 1, 1, 1, 1","c":"2, 3, 3, 3, 3","d":"2, 3, 3, 2, 2","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Sprain is pulling of:","a":"Bone","b":"Ligament of muscles","c":"Cartilage","d":"All of these","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Foramen magnum occurs on:","a":"Lateral side of skull","b":"Posterior side of skull","c":"Anterior side of skull","d":"Neural canal","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Creatine phosphate is present in:","a":"Nervous tissue","b":"Connective tissue","c":"Muscles of vertebrates","d":"Muscles of invertebrates","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Joint between bones of human skull is:","a":"Hinge joint","b":"Synovial joint","c":"Cartilaginous joint","d":"Fibrous joint","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Red muscle fibres are rich in:","a":"Golgi bodies","b":"Mitochondria","c":"Lysosomes","d":"Ribosomes","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"A person is suffering from an age related disorder \"X\". X is characterised by decreased bone mass and increased chances of fractures. Identify X and its common cause.","a":"Tetany, Increased levels of estrogen","b":"Osteoporosis, Decreased levels of estrogen","c":"Myasthenia gravis, Decreased levels of estrogen","d":"Muscular dystrophy, Increased levels of estrogen","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Long uninucleate muscles are found in:","a":"Diaphragm","b":"Alimentary canal","c":"Tongue","d":"Eye","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Obturator foramen occurs in:","a":"Pelvic girdle","b":"Pectoral girdle","c":"Cranium","d":"Vertebrae","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following match is incorrect?","a":"8th 9th and 10th pairs of ribs Do not articulate directly with the sternum but join the sixth rib with the help of hyaline cartilage.","b":"Glenoid cavity-Articulates with the head of the humerus to form the shoulder joint.","c":"Fibrous joint-Flat skull bones which fuse end-to-end with the help of dense fibrous connective tissues in the form of sutures to form the cranium.","d":"Increase in Ca level-Leads to the binding of calcium with a subunit of troponin on actin filaments and thereby remove the masking of active sites for myosin,","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Upon preventing acetylcholine from diffusing across a neuromuscular junction, which of the following will not occur?","a":"No action potential will be produced in the affected muscle fibres.","b":"The endoplasmic reticulum releases calcium ions (Ca) into the cytoplasm.","c":"Myosin will not bind to actin in the affected muscle fibre.Myosin will not bind to actin in the affected muscle fibre.","d":"The affected muscle fibre will fail to contract.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"In human beings, the second cervical vertebra helps in rotatory movements of head through knob-like process called:","a":"Prezygapophysis","b":"Olecranon process","c":"Odontoid process","d":"Metaphysis","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Latissimus dorsi muscles are:","a":"Muscles of fore arm","b":"Muscles of lower jaw","c":"Muscles of the chest","d":"Muscles of the shoulder","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The condition in which a number of nuclei are present in a muscle fibre is called:","a":"Coenocytic","b":"Syncytial","c":"Polykaryon","d":"Endoduplication","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"A stronger muscle contraction occurs when the brain","a":"send signals to larger number of motor units to contract.","b":"activates muscle cells more quickly.","c":"sends nerve impulses to the muscle one at a time instead of in bursts","d":"activates the motor units of the muscle one at a time.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The vertebral column is connected to the pelvic girdle in the:","a":"Coccygeal region","b":"Sacral region","c":"Lumbar region","d":"Cervical region","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which pair does not possess corresponding bones?","a":"Carpals and tarsals","b":"Atlas and coccyx","c":"Pectoral girdle and pelvic girdle","d":"Humerus and femur","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The joint where synovial capsule and synovial fluid are lacking is:","a":"Thick filament","b":"Sarcomere","c":"Myosin molecule","d":"Thin filament","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The number of 'true ribs' in a man is:","a":"12 pair","b":"7 pair","c":"3 pair","d":"2 pair","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Muscle contraction is triggered:","a":"when high levels of oxygen and sugar are released by the sarcolemma.","b":"when a surplus of ATP is released by a nerve motor unit.","c":"by the nerve releasing a neurotransmitter, which triggers a flow of calcium that attaches to actin filaments and exposes the myosin binding sites.","d":"by release of a neurotransmitter at a synapse that directly causes actin and myosin to slide.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"A cricket player is chasing a fast ball in the field. Which one of the following groups of bones are directly contributing in this movement?","a":"Femur, malleus, tibia, metatarsals","b":"Pelvis, ulna, patella, tarsals","c":"Sternum, femur, tibia, fibula","d":"Tarsals, femur, metatarsals, tibia","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following muscles draw the lower jaw, tongue and the head backward?","a":"Proctor","b":"Retractor","c":"Abductor","d":"All of these","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"An example of gliding joint is:","a":"Humerus and glenoid cavity","b":"Femur and tibio-fibula","c":"Zygapophyses of adjacent vertebrae","d":"Occipital condyle and odontoid process","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"A motor unit is best described as:","a":"all the nerve fibres and muscle fibres in a single muscle bundle.","b":"one muscle fibre and its single nerve fibre.","c":"the neuron that provides the CNS with information on the state of contraction of the muscle.","d":"a single motor neuron and all the muscle fibres that it innervates,","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Children sing a song that goes 'head, shoulders, knees, and toes...\" If they sang the names of the bones, it would be (in order))","a":"Hyoid, sternum, patella, and tarsals.","b":"Cranial, clavicle, tibia, and carpals.","c":"Clavicle, carpals, phalanges, and tarsals.","d":"Cranial, scapula, patella, and phalanges.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Synovial fluid is found in:","a":"Cranial cavity","b":"Spinal cavity","c":"Immovable joints","d":"Freely movable joints","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following is incorrect?","a":"Cardiac muscle is striated.","b":"Smooth muscle does not contain actin.","c":"Smooth muscle is found in the iris of the eye and the walls of the bladder.","d":"Skeletal muscle is considered voluntary.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Smallest bone in the human body is:","a":"Stapes","b":"Malleus","c":"Patella","d":"Navicular bone","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Lower jaw of man is made up of:","a":"I bone","b":"2 bones","c":"No bones, only muscles","d":"3 bones","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The action potential that triggers a muscle contraction, travels deep within the muscle cell by means of:","a":"Sarcoplasmic reticulum","b":"Transverse tubules.","c":"Motor end plates","d":"Synapses","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following does not reveal in the detailed analysis of a cilium from the human respiratory tract?","a":"Tubulin","b":"Plasmagel","c":"Microtubules","d":"Axoneme","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Spinal cord passes through:","a":"Foramen of Monro","b":"Foramen ovale","c":"Obturator forament","d":"Foramen magnum","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"In mammals,  the lower jaw is made of:","a":"Maxilla","b":"Dentary","c":"Mandible.","d":"Ethmoid","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Before stimulating the release of calcium ions that causes muscle contraction in skeletal muscle, an action potential must pass through the:","a":"Sarcoplasmic reticulum","b":"T-tubules and sarcoplasmic reticulum","c":"Plasma membrane and T-tubules","d":"Plasma membrane, T-tubules and sarcoplasmic reticulum","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Patella bone is derived from:","a":"Cartilage","b":"Areolar tissue","c":"Tendon","d":"Ligament","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Sigmoid notch is found in:","a":"Tibio-fibula","b":"Femur","c":"Radio-ulna","d":"Humerus","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Zygomatic arch in Rabbit is formed by:","a":"Premaxilla, Maxilla and Palatine","b":"Maxilla, Jugal and Squamosal","c":"Periotic, Maxilla & Premaxilla","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Lower jaw in mammals articulates with a bone called:","a":"Jugal","b":"Alisphenoid","c":"Sqamosal","d":"Parietal","hint":"","correct":"c"}]